Guide to the Edward Farbenblum and Orly Lieberman Collection of Photographs 1924-1993 PR 378
New-York Historical Society
Edward Farbenblum and Orly Lieberman collection of photographs
1924-1993
New-York Historical Society
Farbenblum, Edward
PR 378
4.7 Linear feet in 6 boxes
This collection, assembled and donated by Edward Farbenblum and Orly Lieberman, contains New York Theatre and Hollywood Film portraits and production photos dating from 1924-1993, as well as a small amount of ephemera.
Scope and Contents
This collection, assembled and donated by Edward Farbenblum and Orly Lieberman, contains photographs of and a small amount of ephemera related to New York theatre and Hollywood film productions and personalities. It is organized into two series:
Series I: New York Theatre
Series II: Hollywood Film
Series I: New York Theatre is organized into 4 subseries. The first 3 subseries correlate to the 3 different photography studios that produced the photographs related to New York theatrical productions: Friedman-Abeles Studio, Martha Swope Studio, and Vandamm Studio. The fourth subseries consists of ephemera related to theatrical productions. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject
Most productions depicted in the collection are from Broadway, though some national tours, international troupes such as France's Theatre National Populaire, and off-Broadway programming such as the Brooklyn Academy of Music Next Wave Festival appear. The collection documents the original runs of iconic musicals My Fair Lady, A Little Night Music, A Chorus Line, Oklahoma!, 1776, and Cats (the title most substantially represented in the collection), in addition to new plays, revivals, and multiple iterations of productions such as Cat on a Hot Tin Roof and Tennessee Williams's The Night of the Iguana. Notable subjects include theatre stalwarts such as Lynn Fontanne and Alfred Lunt (in Quadrille) and Robert De Niro (in Last Stand, with Diane Ladd, and later Cuba and His Teddy Bear).
Also present are portraits of Judy Holliday, Helen Hayes, and others, along with a small selection of Swope's ballet and dance photography, including the New York City Ballet and its star ballerina Patricia McBride.
All materials are stamped with photographer's credit and variously include subject name, date, and other information. Some photographs also feature press clippings or publicity captions on the verso.
Series II: Hollywood Film includes publicity and glamour portraits, on-set production shots, and special photography from a variety of studios and photographers such as Clarence Sinclair Bull, George Hurrell, Frank Powolny, and John Egstead. Stars depicted include Katharine Hepburn, Bette Davis, Lana Turner, Clark Gable, Lena Horne, Laurence Olivier, Ava Gardner, Linda Darnell, Ginger Rogers, Lassie the dog, Eve Arden, and Catherine Deneuve.
This series also features an Annie Leibovitz photoshoot with Diane Keaton, Sissy Spacek, and Jessica Lange on the set of Crimes of the Heart (1986), and George Hurrell coverage of the red carpet arrivals at the film premiere of The Rose Tattoo (December 2, 1955), held at the Hotel Astor in New York City.
This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: New York Theatre
Series II: Hollywood Film
Series I: New York Theatre is organized into 4 subseries. The first 3 subseries correlate to the 3 different photography studios that produced the photographs related to New York theatrical productions: Friedman-Abeles Studio, Martha Swope Studio, and Vandamm Studio. The fourth subseries consists of ephemera related to theatrical productions. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series II: Hollywood Film is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward Farbenblum and Orly Lieberman, 2013 and 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Theatrical productions -- New York (State) -- New York -- 1900-2000; Actors -- Portraits; Abeles, Joseph; Friedman, Leo, 1919-2011; Swope, Martha; Vandamm, Florence
- Series I. New York Theatre, 1924-1993; 61852
  Scope and Contents
  Three photographers and studios are represented in the series: Florence Vandamm, of Vandamm Studio (in operation in New York from 1924 to 1964), has been posited as the "inventor" of the commercial head shot and noted for her use of lighting, costume and movement.
  Leo Friedman and Joseph Abeles commenced their publicity photography parternship Friedman-Abeles in 1954 and produced documented the New York theatrical world using their handheld Rolleiflex camera.
  Martha Swope, of Swope Associates, was a former dancer who also began her photographic career in the 1950s and, like Friedman-Abeles, shot backstage activities and the rehearsal process for publicity and documentary purposes.
  Most productions depicted in the collection are from Broadway, though some national tours, international troupes such as France's Theatre National Populaire, and off-Broadway programming such as the Brooklyn Academy of Music Next Wave Festival appear. The collection documents the original runs of iconic musicals My Fair Lady, A Little Night Music, A Chorus Line, Oklahoma!, 1776, and Cats (the title most substantially represented in the collection), in addition to new plays, revivals, and multiple iterations of productions such as Cat on a Hot Tin Roof and Tennessee Williams's The Night of the Iguana. Notable subjects include theatre stalwarts such as Lynn Fontanne and Alfred Lunt (in Quadrille) and a young Robert De Niro (in Last Stand, with Diane Ladd, and later Cuba and His Teddy Bear).
  There are also portraits of Judy Holliday, Helen Hayes, and others, and a small selection of Swope's ballet and dance photography, including the New York City Ballet and its star ballerina Patricia McBride. Additionally, this series contains a small number of Playbill programs, press kit materials, clippings, and ticket stubs.
  - Friedman-Abeles Studio, 1955-1972
    - Theatrical Productions: A-B, 1956-1963; 62461 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      At the Drop of a Hat (1959)
      The Bad Seed (1956)
      Bells are Ringing (1957)
      Beyond the Fringe (1963)
      Bye Bye Birdie (1962)
      The Boy Friend (1957)
    - Theatrical Productions: C, 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Can Can (1956)
      Carnival (1962)
      A Case of Libel (1963)
      Cat on a Hot Tin Roof (1955-56)
      Catch a Star (1955)
    - Theatrical Productions: A Far Country, 1961; 62494 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Productions: E-L, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Eugenia (1957)
      A Far Country (1962)
      Five Finger Exercise (1960)
      Funny Girl (1963)
      The Happiest Millionaire (1958)
      Lil Abner (1957)
    - Theatrical Productions: Last of the Red Hot Lovers, 1970; 62498 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Theatrical Productions: M, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Major Barbara (1957)
      A Man for All Seasons (1963)
      Mary, Mary (1962)
      Much Ado About Nothing (1972)
      Music Man (1960)
      My Fair Lady (1957)
    - Theatrical Productions: N-O, 1962-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      No Time For Sergeants
      Never Too Late (1964)
      No No Nannette (1971)
      Night of the Iguana (1962)
      The Odd Couple (1967)
    - Theatrical Productions: S-Z, 1957-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Strange Interlude (1963)
      Song of the Grasshopper
      Sunrise at Campobello (1958)
      Tchin-Tchin (1962)
      Zeigfield Follies (1957)
    - Theatrical Productions: Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Martha Swope Studio, 1952-1993
    - Theatrical Productions: A, 1977-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Ain't Misbehaving
      Anna Christie (1993)
      Annie (1977)
    - Theatrical Productions: C, 1970-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Castro Complex (1970)
      A Chorus Line (1979)
      Cuba and His Teddy Bear (1986)
    - Theatrical Productions: Cat on a Hot Tin Roof, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Productions: Cats, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    - Theatrical Productions: D-F, 1970-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Dancin' (1983)
      Dreyfus in Rehearsal (1974)
      Endangered Species (1990)
      Forty Carats (1970)
    - Theatrical Productions: G-L, 1970-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      The Good Doctor
      Good Evening
      Hair (1971, 1991)
      Henry V (1984)
      Irene (1973)
      Last Stand (1970)
      A Little Night Music (1973)
    - Theatrical Productions: M-N, 1974-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Man and Superman
      Mary Tudor
      A Map of the World (1985)
      A Moon for the Misbegotten (1974)
      Monty Python
      Night of the Iguana (1976)
    - Theatrical Productions: O-Z, 1952-1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Oh, Kay! (1990)
      On Your Toes (1983)
      Pirates of Penzance (1981)
      Rainbow (1972)
      Suggs in the City (1972)
      Venus Observed (1952)
      1776 (1969)
    - Dance Productions: A-Z, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Don Quixote
      An Evening's Waltzes
      Prodigal Son
      Skater's Waltz [ice dancing]
      A Sketch Book (1978)
      Tricolore
      Trio [ice dancing]
    - Dance Portraits: A-Z, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      John Curry
      Patricia McBride
      Kathleen Moore
      Jimmy Tate
      Unidentified
  - Vandamm Studio, 1924-1959
    - Theatrical Productions: A-B, 1926-1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Affairs of State (1951)
      Amphitryon 38
      Angel in the Wings
      Arms and The Man (1926)
      Bernadine (1952)
      Biography
      Blithe Spirit (1944)
      Boys and Girls Together (1940)
    - Theatrical Productions: C-D, 1933-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Champagne Supper (1933)
      The Comic Artist (1933)
      The Constant Wife (1952)
      Curtains Up (1959)
      The Dark Tower (1933)
      A Date with April (1953)
      The Distaff Side (1934)
      The Doctors Dilemma (1955)
      Duel of Angels
    - Theatrical Productions: A Clearing in the Woods, 1957; 62490 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Productions: The Dark is Light Enough, 1955; 62491 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Theatrical Productions: E-G, 1926-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      End Summer (1936)
      Faithfully Yours
      The Farmer Takes a Wife (1935)
      The Farmer's Wife
      The Firstborn (1958)
      The Great Sebastians
      The Guardsman (1926)
    - Theatrical Productions: The Good Fairy, 1932; 62297 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Theatrical Productions H-J, 1937-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Hear That Trumpet
      Horses in Midstream (1953)
      Idiot's Delight (1937)
      The Importance of Being Earnest
      Interlock
      Janus (1957)
    - Theatrical Productions: L-O, 1932-1951, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
      The Late Christopher Bean (1932)
      Leaf and Bough
      Life With Mother
      Lovers and Friends
      The Man with Blond Hair (1941)
      The Man Who Came to Dinner (1941)
      Mary of Scotland
      Merrily We Roll Along
      The Middle Watch
      The Moon is Blue (1951)
      My Name is Aquilon
      Olympia
    - Theatrical Productions: The Little Hut, 1953; 62500 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Theatrical Productions: Lo and Behold, 1951; 62504 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Theatrical Productions: Oklahoma!, 1951-1954; 62507 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Theatrical Productions: One Bright Day, 1952; 62510 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Theatrical Productions: P-S, 1931-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Parade
      The Play's the Thing
      Porgy
      Precedent (1931)
      Rosalinda (1942)
      Sabrina Flat (1953)
      Showboat (1947)
      Sing and Whistle (1934)
      Sing Me No Lullaby (1954)
      The Searching Wind (1944)
      Set to Music
      Small Miracle (1935)
      Spring Again
      Springtime for Henry (1932)
      Star and Garter
      The Star Wagon (1938)
      Storm Over Patsy (1937)
    - Theatrical Productions: Petticoat Influence, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Theatrical Productions: Quadrille, 1955; 62513 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Theatrical Productions: T-Z, 1924-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
      The Taming of the Shrew (1935)
      There's Always Juliet
      They Knew What They Wanted (1924)
      Three and One (1933)
      Three Men On a Horse
      Time Remembered
      Tomorrow and Tomorrow (1931)
      Washington Jitters
      Watch on the Rhine (1941)
      The Winter's Tale (1945)
      Whistling in the Dark (1932)
      You Never Can Tell (1948)
      You Touched Me!
      The Third Little Show
      This Time Tomorrow
    - Theatrical Productions: The Time of the Cuckoo, 1952; 62516 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Theatrical Productions: Twilight Walk, 1951; 62517 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Theatrical Productions: The Wisteria Trees, 1950; 62519 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Theatrical Portraits: A-Z, 1931-1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Holbrook Blinn
      Kitty Carlisle
      Ina Claire
      Betty Compton
      Peggy Conklin
      Joe Cook
      Constance Cummings
      Ruth Draper
      Clare Eames
      Lynn Fontanne
      Rose Franken
      Ruth Gordon
      Helen Hayes
      Judy Holliday
      Sam Jaffe
      Nancy Kelly
      Earle Larimore
      Pauline Lord
      William Lynn
      Hugh Marlowe
      Burgess Meredith
      Gaby Monet
      Victor Moore
      Reginald Owen
      Mary Phillips
      Barbara Robbins
      June Walker
      Nydia Westman
      Bretaigne Windust
  - Playbills and Publicity Materials, 1969-1990
    - Theatre Productions: Publicity Files - Find Your Way Home, 1974; 62526 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Theatre Productions: Publicity Files - Making Movies, 1990; 62527 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Theatre Productions: Publicity Files - Seven Days of Mourning, 1969; 62528 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series II. Hollywood Film, 1927-1986; 61853
  This series includes publicity and glamour portraits, on-set production shots, and special photography from a variety of studios and photographers such as Clarence Sinclair Bull, George Hurrell, Frank Powolny, and John Egstead. Stars depicted include Katharine Hepburn, Bette Davis, Lana Turner, Clark Gable, Lena Horne, Ava Gardner, Ginger Rogers, Lassie the dog, Eve Arden, and Catherine Deneuve.
  This series also includes an Annie Leibovitz photoshoot with Diane Keaton, Sissy Spacek, and Jessica Lange on the set of Crimes of the Heart (1986), and George Hurrell coverage of the red carpet arrivals at the film premiere of The Rose Tattoo (December 2, 1955), held at the Hotel Astor in New York City.
  - Portraits: A-D, 1927-1960; 61854 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Eve Arden
    Lew Ayres
    Lionel Barrymore
    Warner Baxter
    George Brent
    David Brian
    Dirk Bogarde
    Edwina Booth
    Phyllis Brooks
    Joe E. Brown
    Yul Brynner
    Walter Connolly
    Linda Darnell
    Reginald Denny
  - Portraits: Bette Davis, 1939-1942, undated; 61865 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Portraits: Catherine Deneuve, 1964; 61866 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Portraits: G-K, 1927-1960; 61855 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Clark Gable
    Judy Garland
    Ava Gardner
    Cary Grant
    Fernand Gravet
    Nan Grey
    Mitzi Green
    Jon Hall
    Thurston Hall
    Jean Harlow
    Audrey Hepburn
    Wanda Hendrix
    Ian Hunter
    Joe Jeffries
    Glynis Johns
    Danny Kaye
    Andrea King
    Otto Kruger
  - Portraits: Katharine Hepburn, 1942, undated; 61867 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Portraits: Lena Horne, undated; 61868 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Portraits: L-M, 1927-1960; 61856 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Hedy Lamarr
    Lassie
    Rex Lease
    Viveca Lindfors
    John Loder
    Paul Lukas
    Tully Marshall
    Leora Maricle
    Raymond Massey
    Rosalind Marquis
    Dina Merrill
    Ray Milland
    Elizabeth Montgomery
    Mae Murray
  - Portraits: N-R, 1927-1960; 61857 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Patricia Neal
    Claudette Nevins
    John Neville
    Barbara Nichols
    Doris Nolan
    Joan Perry
    Zasu Pitts
    Tyrone Power
    Frank Powolny
    Jane Randolph
    Phil Regan
    Ginger Rogers
  - Portraits: Laurence Olivier, 1955, undated; 61869 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Portraits: Rosalind Russell, 1945, undated; 61870 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Portraits: S-W, 1927-1960; 61863 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Ann Sheridan
    Clara Lou Sheridan
    Sylvia Sidney
    George E. Stone
    Harry Stockwell
    Elizabeth Taylor
    Ann Todd
    Lana Turner
    Lupe Velez
    Bryant Washburn
    Natalie Wood
    Jane Wyatt
  - Portraits: Unidentified, 1927-1960; 61872 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Film Set: Crimes of the Heart, 1986; 61864 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    photos of Diane Keaton, Sissy Spacek, and Jessica Lange on the set of the film "Crimes of the Heart." The photographs were taken by Annie Leibovitz.
  - Film Premiere: The Rose Tattoo, 1955; 61871 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    photos of red carpet arrivals at the film premiere of "The Rose Tattoo," taken by George Hurrell.